地          球          脉          动
人类总是愿意冒着生命危险 占领地球上最高的地方
Human beings venture into the highest parts of our planet at their peril.
人们或许认为只要登上顶峰
Some might think that by climbing a great mountain
便能征服一座高山
they have somehow conquered it,
不过 我们仅仅只是这里的拜访者
but we can only be visitors here.
这是一个冰封的异域世界
This is a frozen alien world.
雄       伟       高       山
这里是另一种极端环境
This is the other extreme -
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
地球上一处最低最热的地方
one of the lowest hottest places on Earth.
它的地势低于海平面100多米
It's over a hundred metres below the level of the sea.
但这里却在酝酿一座高山
But here a mountain is in gestation.
这些硫酸池暗示 地底深处正进行着大规模活动
Pools of sulphuric acid are indications that deep underground there are titanic stirrings.
这里是埃塞俄比亚境内的达纳吉尔凹地
This is the Danakil Depression in Ethiopia,
位于地球表面的大裂谷内
lying within a colossal rent of the earth's surface
巨大的陆地板块在此互相分离
where giant land masses are pulling away from one another.
熔岩经过这条地壳裂缝涌上地表
Lava rises to the surface through this crack in the crust
诞生了一连串年轻的火山
creating a chain of young volcanoes.
这座埃特阿雷火山
This one, Erta Ale,
是地球上现存持续喷发时间最长的火山
is today the longest continually erupting volcano on the planet,
岩浆湖在此沸腾了100多年
a lake of lava that has been molten for over a hundred years.
这些相同的火山作用 也造就了埃塞俄比亚高原
These same volcanic forces also created Ethiopia's highlands.
7000万年前
70 million years ago
这片土地像达纳吉尔凹地一样平坦深陷
this land was just as flat and as deep as the Danakil Depression.
熔岩从地核中漫涌上来
Molten lava rising from the earth's core
形成了绵延500英里的巨大石丘
forced up a huge dome of rock 500 miles wide,
这就是非洲屋脊
the roof of Africa.
千万年后 雨水和冰川 已将岩石雕琢成尖峰与峡谷
Over millennia, rain and ice carved the rock into a landscape of spires and canyons.
这些将近3英里高的山峰顶上
These summits, nearly 3 miles up,
住着一些非常特别的山地居民
are home to some very remarkable mountaineers -
狮尾狒
Gelada baboons.
它们是埃塞俄比亚高原的特有物种
They are unique to the highlands of Ethiopia.
它们睡觉的悬崖只有 攀岩高手才能爬得上去
The cliffs where they sleep are for expert climbers only,
而狮尾狒则有一套合适的“工具”
and Gelado certainly have the right equipment.
强壮的手指是最主要的
the strongest fingers of any primate
当然也少不了无所畏惧的气概
and an utterly fearless disposition.
不过在这样的高度  要想活下去可不太容易
But you need more than a head for heights to survive up here.
下面将向你展示狮尾狒全天的生活  看看它们如何面对挑战
A day in a Gelado's life reveals how they've risen to the challenge.
对于所有猴子来说  早晨正是“梳妆打扮”的时候
For all monkeys morning is grooming time,
一个交朋友的绝好机会
a chance to catch up with friends.
不过 与其它猴子不同的是
But, unlike other monkeys,
狮尾狒一边这么做 一边还不停地唠叨
Gelados chatter constantly while they do it.
这样手在忙活的同时也能搞好“人际关系”
It's a great way to network while your hands are busy.
但是这种社交活动不会很长
But these socials can't go on for too long.
狮尾狒全天的日程表排得很满
Gelados have a busy daily schedule
还有很多事情要做
and there's work to be done.
大部分猴类都无法在此生存
Most monkeys couldn't live up here.
这里没有食物 可以吃的昆虫也很少
There's no food and few insects to feed on.
但是狮尾狒却很特别
But Gelados are unique -
它们是世界上唯一完全以草为生的猴子
they're the only monkeys in the world that live almost entirely on grass.
它们生活的社群是所有猴类中最大的
They live in the largest assemblies formed by any monkeys.
有的甚至能达到800只
Some groups are 800 strong
如同散布在高山草场上的角马群
and they crop the high meadows like herds of wildebeest.
站在狮尾狒身旁的是西敏羱羊
The Gelados graze alongside Walia ibex,
它们也是这片高原的特有物种
which are also unique to these highlands.
这种罕见的动物通常很胆小
These rare creatures are usually very shy
但只要狮尾狒一来到身边  它们便放松警惕
but they drop their guard when the Gelados are around.
你或许会认为食草动物 总是尽量互相避让
You might expect that grazers would avoid each other's patch
但是这种特殊联盟能使双方都得到好处
but this is a special alliance from which both partners benefit.
它们可以毫无顾虑地埋头吃草
It's not so risky to put your head down
因为旁边有站岗的“哨兵”
if others are on the lookout.
西门豺
Ethiopian wolves -
它们一般不会在大白天发动进攻
they won't attempt an attack in broad daylight.
可是一到傍晚 高原便成了 一个危机四伏的地方
But at dusk the plateau becomes a more dangerous place.
吃草活动基本结束
With the grazing largely over
狮尾狒们抓住最后一点机会进行社交  然后返回睡觉的悬崖
there's a last chance to socialise before returning to the sleeping cliffs.
“即时预警系统”使大家都警觉起来
An early warning system puts everyone on the alert.
这一天结束了 和开始时一样  它们又坐在了陡峭而安全的悬崖上
Their day ends as it began, safe on the steep cliffs.
埃塞俄比亚的火山正处于休眠期
The Ethiopian volcanoes are dormant,
可是其它地方的火山仍在怒吼
but elsewhere others still rage.
火山构成了地球上最长山系的主干
Volcanoes form the backbone of the longest mountain chain on our planet -
南美洲的安第斯山脉
the Andes of South America.
这座巨大的山脉 从赤道向南极绵亘5000英里
This vast range stretches 5,000 miles from the Equator down to the Antarctic.
它的形成是由于太平洋板块
It formed as the floor of the Pacific Ocean
俯冲到南美洲板块之下  造成它的边缘隆起
slid beneath the South American continent, buckling its edge.
最南端矗立着巴塔哥尼亚山脉
At the southern end stand the mountains of Patagonia.
现在是盛夏时节
It's high summer,
可是安第斯山的天气 是全球山区气候中最不稳定的
but the Andes have the most unstable mountain weather on the planet
暴风雪会在毫无征兆的情况下来袭
and storms can erupt without warning.
气温直线下降
Temperatures plummet
羊驼和它们新生的幼仔 只好忍受突如其来的风雪
and guanacos and their newborn young must suddenly endure a blizzard.
可以说是在一天之中度过了四季
Truly, all seasons in one day...
美洲狮
A puma -
安第斯山区的狮子
the lion of the Andes.
美洲狮通常独来独往 隐秘莫测
Pumas are usually solitary and secretive.
这么一大家子在光天化日之下 外出实属罕见
To see a group walking boldly in the open is extremely rare.
这个家庭由一只母狮和4只小狮组成
It's a family - a mother with four cubs.
母狮只能利用这个短暂的夏天 教会小狮在山区生存的技能
She has just one brief summer in which to teach them their mountain survival techniques.
把4只小狮养到这么大 是很了不起的业绩
Rearing four cubs to this age is an exceptional feat,
那是因为它有一片富饶的领地
but she does have an excellent territory,
食物和水都很充足
rich in food and water.
虽然小狮已长到和它们的母亲差不多大
Although the cubs are now as large as their mother,
它们仍需要依靠母狮获取食物
they still rely on her for their food.
小狮至少还需要一年时间 才能学会独自狩猎
It will be another year before the cubs can hunt for themselves.
如果没有母狮的技术和经验
Without their mother's skill and experience
它们肯定无法活过第一个冬天
they would never survive their first winter.
凛冽的山风在崖坡上呼啸肆虐  生命根本无法在此扎根
Battered by hurricane force winds, these slopes are now lifeless.
在更远的北方 它们还潜藏着其它危险
Further north, they hold other dangers.
雪崩时速可达250英里/小时  足以摧毁路过的一切
Moving at 250 miles an hour, an avalanche destroys everything in its path.
位于美国的落基山脉
In the American Rockies
每年冬季会发生10万次毁灭性的雪崩
a 100,000 avalanches devastate the slopes every winter.
巨大的山系脊梁从巴塔哥尼亚 一直延伸到阿拉斯加
This huge mountain chain continues the great spine that runs from Patagonia to Alaska.
尽管落基山地荒凉凄冷
The slopes of the Rockies, bleak though they are,
却能为一些动物提供越冬场所
provide a winter refuge for some animals.
灰熊妈妈正走出巢穴
A mother grizzly emerges from her den
长达6个月的地下冬眠结束了
after six months' dozing underground.
两只小熊紧跟着它们的母亲
Her two cubs follow her
第一次踏足这个陌生的户外世界
and take their first steps in the outside world.
这些陡峭的斜坡也是小熊的庇护所
These steep slopes provide a sanctuary for the cubs.
公熊只要有机会就会吃掉它们
A male bear would kill and eat them given the chance.
不过大型动物很难爬到这个地方
But big animals find it difficult to get about here.
公熊体型可能是母熊的2倍
Males may be twice the size of a female
但即使是母熊也已是举步艰难
and even she can have problems.
可是它的幼崽在雪地里却是轻松自如  体型也和一般动物差不多
Her cubs, however, make light of the snow and of life in general.
母熊面临着一个进退两难的选择
But the mother faces a dilemma:
它已经6个月没有吃东西了
it's six months since she last fed
它的乳汁也即将耗尽
and her milk is starting to run dry.
它必须尽快离开这个安全的斜坡“托儿所”
She must soon leave the safety of these nursery slopes
把它的幼崽带离山地
and lead her cubs away from the mountain.
若是稍有耽搁 整个家族就会面临饥荒
If she delays, the whole family will risk starvation.
夏天揭露了落基山的真实面目
Summer reveals the true nature of the Rockies.
剥去雪层之后
Stripped of snow,
山峰裸露出斧凿般的造型
the peaks bear their sculpted forms.
山地动物只有此时才能 向更高的地方拓展疆土
Only now can mountaineers reclaim the upper reaches.
两英里高的碎石崖上 似乎不可能有生命存在
Two miles up the crumbling precipices seem devoid of life.
可是那里仍有动物
But there are animals here -
一只灰熊
a grizzly bear.
很奇怪这样的动物为何 会爬到如此高的碎石斜坡上
It seems to be an odd creature to find on these high rocky slopes.
真不知道这里有什么吸引着它
It's hard to imagine what could have attracted it here.
在每年的这个时候  熊必须为越冬储备脂肪
At this time of the year bears should be fattening up for the winter.
然而却有一定数量的灰熊 聚集在这片不毛之地
Yet they gather in some numbers on these apparently barren slopes.
它们正在寻找一种很特别的食物
They're searching for a rather unusual food -
飞蛾
moths.
为了躲避低洼地带的炎热  数百万只飞蛾抵达此地
Millions have flown up here to escape the heat of the lowlands
栖身于岩石缝隙之中
and they're now roosting among the rocks.
飞蛾似乎并不足以填饱熊的肚子
Moths may seem a meager meal for a bear,
但它们身体内富含脂肪
but their bodies are rich in fat
直接关系到灰熊每年冬天的生存能力
and can make all the difference in a bear's annual struggle for survival.
这里又开辟了一个新的战场
Another battle is being waged here
可是不会持续多久
but on a much longer timescale.
这些散落的石块是从山脊上崩裂下来的
These loose boulders are the mountain's crumbling bones.
落基山脉已不再上升
The Rockies are no longer rising
却是在慢慢地崩塌
but slowly disintegrating.
世界各地的高山都在不断经受 森林、积雪和冰川的消蚀
All mountains everywhere are being worn down by frost, snow and ice.
阿尔卑斯山崛起于1500万年前
The Alps were raised some 15 million years ago
原因是非洲板块向北漂移  与欧洲南麓相撞
as Africa, drifting northwards, collided with the southern edge of Europe.
曾经连接两块大陆的古老海床 侵蚀后留下了一座座尖耸的山峰
These spires are the eroded remains of an ancient seabed that once stretched between the two continents.
可是这些只是阿尔卑斯山麓地带的小山
But these are just the Alpine foothills.
山脉中心地带的山峰伫立高达3英里
The range at its centre rises to 3 miles high
并且终年覆盖积雪
and is crowned with permanent snows.
马特洪峰
The Matterhorn,
高峻挺拔的峰顶甚至无法附着积雪
its summit too steep to hold a snow field.
勃朗峰——西欧最高的山峰
Mont Blanc - the highest peak in Western Europe.
阿尔卑斯山峰具有与众不同的尖齿状外形
The distinctive jagged shapes of the Alps
这些杰作出自一位伟大的山峰雕刻家之手
were carved by those great mountain sculptors -
冰川
the glaciers.
一望无际的流动冰河
Immense rivers of moving ice,
满载着岩石
laden with rock,
碾磨出一座座尖峭的山峰
grind their way down the mountains,
刨削出一个个深邃的山谷
gouging out deep valleys.
它是地球上最大的侵蚀作用
They're the most powerful erosive force on our planet.
冰川瓯穴——由冰融水凿成的 直达冰川深处的圆筒状竖井
A moulin - a shaft in the ice opened by melt water as it plunges into the depths of the glacier.
正如奔腾不息的流水
Like the water running through it,
冰川也在不断移动
the ice itself is constantly moving,
一刻不停地刨蚀着深谷
flowing down the valley with unstoppable force.
阿尔卑斯冰川看起来已是无边无际
Alpine glaciers may seem immense,
但它仍比不上分隔印度次大陆 和西藏的巨大山脉中的冰川
but they're dwarfed by those in the great ranges that divide the Indian subcontinent from Tibet.
这片巨石滩嘴属于巨大的巴尔托洛冰川  位于巴基斯坦境内的喀喇昆仑山脉
This is the boulder strewn snout of the giant Baltoro glacier in the Karakoram mountains of Pakistan.
它是地球上最大的山丘冰川
It's the biggest mountain glacier on Earth -
长43英里 宽3英里多
43 miles long and over 3 miles wide.
这座冰封山谷巨大无比
This huge ice-filled valley is so large
即使在太空中也能看得很清楚
it's clearly visible from space.
这里是地球上5英里以上高峰最集中的地方
This is the greatest concentration of peaks over 5 miles high to be found anywhere on Earth.
它们是最危险的山峰
They're the most dangerous mountains of all.
乔戈里峰和它的姊妹峰夺去的生命 比其它山峰都要多得多
K2 and her sister peaks have claimed more lives than any others.
这里的山峰极为险峻
The peaks here rise so precipitously,
冰川陡峭易碎
the glaciers are so steep and crevassed
纵使最有经验的登山运动员 也很难征服这些高山
that few except the most skilled mountaineers can penetrate these ranges.
捻角山羊正在举行年度聚会
Markhor gather for their annual rut.
公羊必须为争夺生育权而战斗
Males must fight for the right to breed,
在如此峻峭的崖壁上  哪一方滑倒都有可能直接送命
but on these sheer cliffs any slip by either animal could be fatal.
雪豹
A snow leopard -
喜马拉雅地区最稀有的动物
the rarest of Himalayan animals.
这是只母豹 正要返回巢穴
It's a female returning to her lair.
这是在野外环境中 第一次近距离拍摄雪豹
These are the first intimate images of snow leopard ever filmed in the wild.
它在向自己一岁大的幼崽问好
She greets her one year old cub.
它的巢穴选址不错
Her den is well chosen.
非常适于观望周围崖壁的情况
It has exceptional views of the surrounding cliffs.
在这些变化莫测的悬崖上
On these treacherous slopes
没有其它掠食者能和雪豹一样
no hunter other than the snow leopard
有机会逮住这些羸弱的猎物
would have a chance of catching such fragile prey.
一只母羊和几只小羊羔 是最容易下手的目标
A female with young makes an easier target.
它那宽大的脚爪具备很好的抓地力
Her large paws give an excellent grip
长尾巴能保持身体平衡
and that long tail helps her balance.
它静悄悄地来到猎物上方
Silently she positions herself above her prey.
这一次它无功而返
She returns with nothing.
金雕在悬崖边巡视  搜寻着老弱病残的动物
Golden eagles patrol these cliffs in search of the weak or injured.
靠着两米长的翼展
With a 2 metre wing span
这些大鸟能轻松抓起一只小羊羔
this bird could easily take a young markhor.
金雕捕猎靠的是视力
Eagles hunt by sight
雪越下越密 它们只好选择放弃
and the thickening veil of snow forces them to give up.
不过雪却能为雪豹提供掩护
For the leopard the snow provides cover
使它有机会捕猎
and creates an opportunity.
恶劣的天气掩盖了它逼近的脚步声
The worsening weather dampens the sound of her approach
它正逐渐进入攻击范围
allowing her to get within striking distance.
它已被逼上了绝路
It was an act of desperation
所以才会捕捉如此大的动物
to try and catch such a large animal.
狼刚进行完一场屠杀
Wolves have made a kill
为其它掠食者留下了残存的肢体
giving other hunters a chance to scavenge.
肆虐的风雪终于使雪豹成功了一回
The worst of the blizzard brings success for the snow leopard,
不过作为自古以来的狩猎方式
but having descended so far to make the kill
它得费很大气力才能把猎物拖回家中
she has a grueling climb to get back to her lair.
小豹只能耐心等待
The cub must be patient.
它至少需要一年时间才能有足够的技巧和力量 在这些艰险的峭壁上独自狩猎
It'll be a year before it has the strength and skill to kill for itself on these difficult slopes.
雪豹是一种几乎被神化了的动物
The snow leopard is an almost mythical creature,
它们是荒野的标志
an icon of the wilderness,
这种动物只有很少一部分人亲眼见过
an animal few humans have ever glimpsed
因为我们很少涉足它们的世界
for its world is one we seldom visit.
喀喇昆仑座落在另一座山脉的西侧
The Karakoram lie at the western end of a range
这座山脉绵延长达地球圆周的1/10
that stretches across a tenth of our planet -
它就是喜马拉雅山脉
the Himalayas.
这些世界上最高的山峰
These, the highest mountains of the world,
与其它大型山脉一样
like other great ranges,
也是由于大陆板块相撞而形成的
were created by the collision of continents.
大约5千万年前
Some 50 million years ago
印度次大陆撞上西藏
India collided with Tibet
挤压形成的这些巨大山峰 至今仍在不断升高
thrusting up these immense peaks, which are still rising.
这条岩石与冰川组成的巨幅屏障极其宽广  甚至能改变全球气候
This vast barrier of rock and ice is so colossal it shapes the world's climate.
印度吹来的暖风满载着水气
Warm winds from India, full of moisture,
经由喜马拉雅山脉抬升
are forced upwards by the Himalayas.
上升的气流逐渐变冷
As the air rises so it cools,
形成云团
causing clouds to form
从而产生了季风雨
and the monsoon is born.
高海拔地区的季风雨变成了雪
At high altitudes the monsoon rains fall as snow.
这里是中国境内的山脉东部起点
Here, at the far eastern end of the range in China,
有一位居民在户外忍受着严冬的寒冷
one inhabitant endures the bitter winters out in the open.
现在其它大部分熊都已躲在地下睡大觉
Most other bears would be sleeping underground by now,
可是大熊猫没能储备足够的脂肪冬眠
but the giant panda can't fatten up enough to hibernate.
它完全依赖竹子为生
Its food, bamboo, on which it totally relies
但是竹叶没有太多营养价值
has so little nutritional value
所以它无法像别的熊那样积累起脂肪
that it can't build up a store of fat like other bears.
这里的大部分动物 都随着季节变化上下迁移
Most of the creatures here move up or down the slopes with the seasons
只有大熊猫因为食物始终逗留此地
but the panda is held captive by its diet
它吃的这种竹子只生长在这一海拔地区
for the kind of bamboo it eats only grows at this altitude.
不过这些森林对于更灵活的动物来说 却没有什么挑战性
But these forests hold fewer challenges for the more mobile.
和大熊猫一样  川金丝猴只生活在中国境内
The golden snap-nosed monkey, like the giant panda, lives only in China.
它们有厚实的毛发  所以能比其它猴类更能适应高海拔气候
Their thick fur allows them to survive at greater altitudes than any other monkey
每当严寒袭来  这些山坡就成了它们的天下
and when the cold bites they have these upper slopes to themselves.
虽然有了暖和的“大衣”
Even if you have a warm coat
最好还是与尽可能多的伙伴 挤在一起保暖
it apparently helps to surround yourself with as many layers as possible.
这些猴子至少还有一个选择
But at least these monkeys have a choice -
如果它们厌倦了树皮和其它残存的食物
if they tire of tree bark and other survival food
便会搬迁到温暖的低海拔地区
they can always descend to lower warmer altitudes
等到春天再返回此地
and not return there till spring.
冰雪消融
As the snows retreat
万木逢春
trees come into bloom.
樱花
Cherry blossom.
杜鹃花
Rhododendrons -
它们在大自然中形成大片灌木林
here in their natural home they form great forests
为这幅季候风景画抹上一笔浓艳的色彩
and fill the landscape with the covers of a new season.
这些灌木林也是许多种春季候鸟的家园
These forests are a host to a rich variety of springtime migrants.
花丛下别有一番景象
Beneath the blooms - another display.
现在正是亚洲雉的交配季节
It's the mating season for oriental pheasants,
棕尾虹雉
Himalayan monal,
角雉
tragopan
还有血雉
and blood pheasant.
许多春季食物才刚露面不久  便已被麝鹿一扫而光
Musk deer make the most of a short flash of spring foods.
这只公鹿闻到了未来配偶的气味
This male smells a potential mate.
小熊猫在野外十分罕见
The red panda, rarely glimpsed in the wild.
它曾经被认为是浣熊的一种
It was once considered a kind of raccoon,
现在已被确认为一种小型山地熊类
but is now believed to be a small mountain bear.
到了仲夏 它那更大更有名的亲戚 便会躲进山洞
By midsummer its larger, more famous relative, has retreated into a cave.
这只大熊猫正在照顾刚满一周的小宝宝
A giant panda nurses a tiny week old baby.
轻柔的清洁是为了防止感染
Her tender cleaning wards off infection.
未来3周内 它都不会离开这个山洞
She won't leave this cave for three weeks,
否则它的幼崽将彻底无依无靠
not while her cub is so utterly helpless.
幼崽生长得很慢
Progress is slow
因为由竹子转化来的乳汁少得可怜
for milk produced on a diet of bamboo is wretchedly poor.
小家伙已经4周大了 可仍旧看不见东西
Four weeks old and the cub is still blind.
直到出生后的第3个月  它的眼睛才能完全睁开
Its eyes do not fully open until three months after birth,
但是熊猫幼崽长到成年的机会极为渺茫
but the chances of the cub reaching adulthood are slim.
大熊猫努力养育幼崽的情景
The struggle of a giant panda mother to raise her cub
真是大山里濒危生命求生的动人一幕
is a touching symbol of the precariousness of life in the mountains.
在地球上最高的地方
On the highest summits of our planet
没有什么生物能在此永久生存
nothing can live permanently.
世界上最高的山峰
The highest peak of all,
海拔5.5英里的世界屋脊 ——珠穆朗玛峰仍在不断升高
Mount Everest, five and a half miles above sea level and still rising - the roof of our world.
在试图登顶珠峰的人中
Of those humans who've tried to climb it
有1/10失去了生命
one in ten have lost their lives.
而成功的人们也只能在峰顶短暂逗留
Those that succeed can stand for only a few moments on its summit.
尼泊尔人称之为 “一座高得连鸟也飞不上去的山峰”
The Nepalese call it 'a mountain so high no bird can fly above it.'
可是 5万多只蓑羽鹤每年都会 进行一场地球上最具挑战性的迁徙
But each year over 50,000 demoiselle cranes set out on one of the most challenging migrations on Earth.
要想到达印度境内的越冬场所
To reach their overwintering grounds in India
它们必须跨越喜马拉雅山脉
they must cross the Himalayas.
晌午时分 群山间狂风大作
By late morning ferocious winds are roaring past the peaks.
鹤群必须提升高度  躲避正在形成的风暴
The cranes must gain height to avoid the building storm.
它们遇上了一股强力气旋
They've hit serious turbulence.
它们只好掉头返回
They must turn back
否则就会送命
or risk death.
新的一天
A new day
新的机遇
and a new opportunity.
鹤群通过互相鸣叫保持密切联系
The flock stay in close contact by calling one another.
尽管它们缺食少水 日渐衰弱
Weak from lack of food and water,
可它们会利用热空气 ——呈圆柱形上升的热气流来获取高度
they use thermals, rising columns of warm air, to gain height.
许多蓑羽鹤都是第一次 踏上穿越喜马拉雅的旅程
For many this is their first journey across the Himalayas.
而有些却是最后一次
For some, it will be their last.
金雕早已企待它们的到来
The golden eagles have been expecting them.
两只金雕合作将一只小鹤 从队伍中分离出来
The eagles work in pairs to separate a young crane from the flock.
它躲过了其中一只的追捕
It escapes the touches of one,
却没能逃过另一只的利爪
and is caught by another.
一只小鹤的份量也是挺重的
But even a young crane is a heavy prize
金雕不得不努力控制飞行
and the eagle has to struggle to control it.
母鹤可不能等得太久
The mother can wait no longer -
这是一场与恶劣气候的死亡赛跑
this is a desperate race against worsening weather.
鹤群其它成员开始背水一战
The rest of the flock battle on.
上升过程中每扇一下翅膀 都得用尽全身气力
In the ascent every wing beat becomes an exhausting struggle.
最后它们终于翻越了旅途中最高的障碍
At last they are over the highest barrier that lies in their way.
不过 与所有高山世界的拜访者一样
But like all who visit the world of the high mountains
它们也不敢逗留
they dare not linger.